Guide to the William North Rice Papers, 1861 - 1955 (bulk 1861 - 1928)
William North Rice Papers, 1861 - 1955 (bulk 1861 - 1928)
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Rice, William North, 1845-1928.
1000-123
4.5
10
William North Rice (1845-1928) was a graduate and long-time faculty member and administrator at Wesleyan University. As a student, he was a member of Phi Nu Theta. He was known as a scientist, minister, and educational expert.
The William North Rice Papers contain diaries, correspondence, account books, teaching materials, writings, lectures, and sermons related to Rice's interests in Wesleyan University, science, religion, and education in general. Specific topics include coeducation at Wesleyan University, campus politics and activities, and issues related to students, faculty, and trustees. Rice's interests in geology, botany, mineralogy, crystallography, and zoology are represented, as is his interest in the relationship between science and religion.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Donated by William Abbott Rice in December 1960.
Alternate Finding Aids
An older, printed finding aid is also available for use in Special Collections & Archives.
Biographical Note
Born in 1845, William North Rice, of Springfield, Massachusetts, entered Wesleyan University in August 1861 at the age of fifteen. He graduated in 1865 as the valedictorian of his class, and went on to the Sheffield Scientific School at Yale University to receive the first Ph.D. awarded in the United States in geology in 1867. After further study in Europe, he returned to Wesleyan to teach natural science courses, a very new field in the existing academic world of Greek and Latin literature and mathematics.
He served as Professor of Geology and Natural History, 1868-1884; G.I. Seney Professor of Geology, 1884-1918; G.I. Seney Professor of Geology Emeritus, 1918-1928; and as acting president of the university, 1907, 1908-1909, and 1918. He died 13 November 1928, after a 67-year association with Wesleyan.
Rice was distinguished not only for his knowledge of geological formations throughout the mountains of Connecticut and Massachusetts, but also for his many publications and sermons as a Methodist minister.
In addition, Rice was a prolific writer. Along with several books, he wrote dozens of sermons and lectures which were published in newspapers and journals. He was a frequent contributor to Zion's Herald, a religious publication of the Boston Wesleyan Assocation, as well as to other religious and secular newspapers. His writings often dealt with the conflict many people experienced, in the first half-century after the publictaion of Darwin's Origin of the Species, between new scientific thought and Biblical tradition. Other lectures and sermons were strictly theological in nature.
Collection Overview
The William North Rice Papers contain diaries, correspondence, account books, teaching materials, writings, lectures, and sermons related to Rice's interests in Wesleyan University, science, religion, and education in general. The Diaries and Correspondence series includes personal diaries and account books kept by William North Rice during his time as a Wesleyan University student, and correspondence from family members, friends, colleagues, and fellow alumni from throughout his life. The subject of many of the diary entries and letters is Wesleyan University, and these writings contain information about academics, social life, campus groups, co-education, trustee maters, campus politics, selection of presidents, alumni affairs, coeducation, student discipline, and faculty recruitment.
The Teaching and Education series includes record books, lecture notes, examination questions, and tributes and memorials. The record books record student grades for the courses taught by Rice. His lecture notes cover subjects including botany, geology, mineralogy and crystallography, zoology and science and religion. The examination questions include those used by Rice in his own teaching, as well as entrance examination questions for Wesleyan University and other New England colleges and universities. The tributes and memorials to Rice, as well as obituaries, offer information about Rice's teaching and scholarly career. Also included in this series is a hand-drawn sketch of Rice made by Mrs. Calvin Sears Harrington.
The Publications, Addresses, and Sermons series contains materials created by Rice on the topics of Wesleyan University, education, geology and science, and religion. An index of sermons and publications can be found at the beginning of the series.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Rice, William North, 1845-1928.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Administration.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Alumni and alumnae.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Students.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --Greek letter societies.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.) --History.; Religion and science.; Christianity.; Geology.; Mineralogy.; Crystallography.; Diaries.; Botany.; Zoology.; Coeducation --United States.; Education, Higher.
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Special Collections & Archives Vertical Files and in other archival collections. Please contact Special Collections & Archives for more information.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Diaries and Correspondence, 1861-1927
  The Diaries and Correspondence series includes personal diaries and account books kept by William North Rice during his time as a Wesleyan University student, and correspondence from family members, friends, colleagues, and fellow alumni from throughout his life.
  Diaries date from Rice's years as a student at Wesleyan, and include information about academics, social life, campus groups, and other Wesleyan-related observations. Some transcripts, made by Rice's grandson, are available in this collection as well. The "Letters Home from Wesleyan" were mainly written to Rice's father, William Rice, who served on the Wesleyan Board of Trustees. Some of these letters also include paragraphs separately addressed to other family members. Other letters were specifically addressed to other family members. Other correspondence addresses the issue of coeducation at Wesleyan during its first phase of admitting female students. There is also congratulatory correspondence regarding Rice's 50th anniversary of graduation from Wesleyan and his 80th birthday. Rice also corresponded frequently with his son about Wesleyan topics.
  The final part of this series consists of letters arranged by the last name of the correspondent. Most of these writers were Wesleyan alumni, and most only wrote one or two letters. Topics include opinions on trustee matters, campus politics, selection of presidents, alumni affairs, coeducation, student discipline, and faculty recruitment.
  - Diary, January 1861-January 1863 (Volume 1)
  - Diary, January 1864-February 1865 (Volume 2)
  - Diary, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account book, August 1861-December 1862 (Folder 2)
  - Account book, January 1864-July 1867 (Folder 3)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 23 August-29 December 1861 (Folder 4)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 5 January-28 May 1862 (Folder 5)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 2 June-28 December 1862 (Folder 6)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 4 January-30 May 1863 (Folder 7)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 9 June-19 December 1863 (Folder 8)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 4 January-25 June 1864 (Folder 9)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 6 July-31 December 1864 (Folder 10)
  - Letters home from Wesleyan, 21 January-13 July 1865 (Folder 11)
  - Letters from WNR to various persons, 1862-1925 (Folder 12)
  - Letters to WNR from his father, 1868-1897 (Folder 13)
  - Letters to WNR from relatives, 1870-1918 (Folder 14)
  - Elizabeth W. C. Rice letters, 1882, 1905 (Folder 15)
    1882 letter contains news and anecdotes about members of the Wesleyan community in 1882, male and female, old and young.
    This file was transferred from Special Collections & Archives Vertical Files in 2006.
  - Correspondence regarding co-education, 1909 (Folder 16)
  - Correspondence regarding co-education and other Wesleyan topics, 1868-1910 (Folder 17)
    This folder of letters was separated from the rest of the William North Rice collection until 2006. Researchers using the collection prior to 2006 would not have seen these letters.
  - Letters to WNR on 50th anniversary of graduation from Wesleyan, 1915 (Folder 18)
  - Letters to WNR on his 80th birthday, 1925 (Folder 19)
  - Letters to son E. L. Rice, 1896-1927 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Transcripts of diaries and letters, 1861-1862 (Folder 8)
  - Transcripts of diaries and letters, 1862-1863 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Transcripts of diaries and letters, 1864 (Folder 2)
  - Transcripts of diaries and letters, 1864-1865 (Folder 3)
  - Transcripts of writings on Phi Nu Theta (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to WNR
    These letters contain important information and opinions on trustee matters, campus politics, selection of presidents, alumni affairs, coeducation, student discipline, and faculty recruitment. Most of the correspondents were Wesleyan alumni, and almost all wrote fewer than ten letters. Most wrote only one or two. The correspondents who wrote ten or more letters are: W. O. Atwater, J. Beech, J. Cunnings, L. Magee, J. Mudge, F. M. North, S. H. Olin, H. L. Osborn, and B. P. Raymond.
    - Abbott, J. E., 1872 (Box 4)
    - Albro, A. B., 1905
    - Anderson, W. H., 1888
    - Allison, D., 1873
    - Andrews, E. G., 1869, 1897-1903
    - Armstrong, A. C., 1904-1911
    - Atwater, C. W., 1922
    - Atwater, W. O., 1872-1891, undated
    - Bacheller, A. L., undated
    - Bagnall, W. R., 1891
    - Bailey, M. A., 1920
    - Barnhart, J. H., 1893-1895
    - Beattys, F. D., 1909
    - Beattys, H. H., 1894
    - Beattys, F. D., 1891
    - Beech, J., 1902-1927, undated
    - Berry, W. F., 1888-1904
    - Bisbee, R. E., 1881-1904
    - Bowdish, W. W., 1869
    - Brodhead, G., undated
    - Brundage, W. M., 1890
    - Buckley, J. M., 1897
    - Burke, J. C., 1883-1884
    - Burnes, H. E., 1894
    - Burnett, W. A., 1865-1866
    - Chadbourne, G. S., 1886
    - Chanter, W. G., 1919
    - Chase, A. F., 1881-1883
    - Chase, John L., 1894
    - Chattaway, S. M., 1881
    - Clark, J. C., 1886
    - Clarke, F. W., 1870
    - Coffin, S. V., 1889
    - Conklin, E. G., 1922
    - Cooper, R. W., 1909
    - Cramer, N. L., 1875
    - Crawford, J., 1915
    - Crawford, M. B., 1877-1888
    - Crittenden, A. R., 1903
    - Crowell, L., 1884-1889
    - Crowell, S. F., 1912
    - Cunnings, J., 1840
    - Curtice, S. O., 1897
    - Dallinger, L., 1886
    - Davenport, F. M., 1897-1915
    - Davis, C. E., 1882, 1903
    - Davis, C. H., 1905-1909
    - Davis, H. L., 1904
    - Davis, W. B., 1909
    - Dennis, A. P., 1897
    - Develin, J. A., undated
    - Dickinson, J., 1879
    - Downey, D., 1903-1916
    - Dutcher, G. M., 1922
    - Eckfeldt, T. H., 1886
    - Edgerton, F. D., 1890
    - Eggleston, A. C., 1876
    - Eustis, J. E., 1876
    - Farrand, Max, 1904
    - Faulkner, J. A., 1897
    - Faulks, J. B., 1889-1902
    - Fearon, R. N., 1869
    - Fisk, H. F., 1865-1873
    - Foss, C. D., 1878-1907
    - Foye, W. G., 1925
    - Furber, D. B., 1877-1884
    - Garrison, S., 1895
    - Gilbert, L., 1884
    - Gill, B., 1890, 1904
    - Gilman, B. A., 1882, 1902
    - Godard, G. S., 1910
    - Goode, G. B., 1872-1896, undated
    - Gordy, J. P., 1886-1903
    - Gowdy, J., 1897
    - Graham, J. C., 1893-1907
    - Graves, A. S., 1865
    - Guss, R. W., 1903
    - Haley, J. F., 1878
    - Hall, G. A., 1873
    - Hall, Mary, 1890
    - Harriman, D. G., 1874
    - Harriman, H. I., 1920
    - Harris, A. W., 1910
    - Haven, E. O., 1872
    - Haven, G., 1874
    - Hewitt, J. W., 1908
    - Hoagland, M. L., 1866, 1899
    - Hibbard, R. G., 1876
    - Hotchkiss, A., 1892
    - Howland, C. P., 1890
    - Hoyt, F. S., 1879-1890
    - Hubbard, C. D., 1874-1888
    - Hubbard, W. P., 1870-1908
    - Hunt, A. S., 1887-1894
    - Hutchison, H. C., 1891
    - Hyde, A. B. 1872-1882
    - Ingraham, H. C. M., 1874-1909
    - James, W. J., 1891-1898
    - Johnston, A. K., 1869-1880
    - Johnston, J., 1876
    - Johnston, Mrs. J., 1866
    - Johnston, M. M., 1874
    - Johnston, W. A., 1903
    - Judd, O., 1871-1883
    - Judkin, C. O., undated
    - Kelley, W. V., 1903-1927
    - Kent, S. W., 1874
    - Knapp, M. A., 1886-1905
    - Kynett, A. G., 1879
    - Landon, T. H., 1885-1902
    - Larkin, G. R., 1923
    - Leavenworth, C., 1900
    - Lindsay, T. B., 1876
    - Lippit, C., 1864
    - Littlefield, C., 1914
    - Loper, S. W., 1890-1898
    - Loveland, A. E., 1897
    - Lyon, Asa, 1876
    - MacMullen, W., 1897 (Box 5)
    - Magee, L., 1885
    - Mains, G. P., 1878-1904
    - Mallalieu, W. F., 1870, 1903
    - Mann, A., 1895
    - Mansfield, John H., 1869
    - Mansfield, Joseph H., undated
    - Manship, W. S., 1911
    - Marcy, C. D., 1915
    - Marcy, O., 1866
    - Marsh, T. P., 1879
    - McConaughy, J. L., 1927
    - McCormick, C. W., 1891-1892
    - Merrill, E. T., 1886-1891
    - Millard, C. W., 1903
    - Monroe, H. K., 1903-1907
    - Morse, J. L., 1879
    - Mudge, J., 1870-1915
    - Munson, J. O., 1885
    - Neumann, G. B., 1923-1925
    - Newhall, F. N., 1881, undated
    - Newton, C. L., 1927
    - Newton, H. G., 1903
    - Newton, L., undated
    - Newton, W. M., 1916
    - Nicols, H., 1894
    - Nicolson, F., 1910
    - Niles, W., 1870
    - North, C. J., 1882-1898
    - North, C. R., 1872
    - North, E., 1914
    - North, F. M., 1872
    - Norton, L. L., 1900
    - Olin, S. H., 1871-1925, undated
    - Opdyke, L. A., 1890-1904
    - Osborn, H. L., 1879-1915
    - Osborne, W. F., 1876-1882
    - Parker, F. H., 1898,1914
    - Parker, R. C., 1908
    - Pease, C., 1899
    - Peck, E. J., undated
    - Pettee, J., undated
    - Phillips, W., 1865
    - Pickard, H., 1889
    - Platt, S. H., undated
    - Plimpton, G. L., 1899-1900
    - Pullman, J., 1877-1899, undated
    - Raymond, B. P., 1888-1909
    - Rand, J. C., 1870-1881, undated
    - Reynolds, F., 1874
    - Reynolds, G. G., 1906-1927
    - Rice, W. M., 1889-1903
    - Rich, H. L., 1890
    - Richard, E. M., 1904
    - Richard, W. A., 1903
    - Richards, T., 1917
    - Roe, A. S., 1876
    - Rosa, E. B., 1887-1890
    - Round, G. C., 1900, 1915
    - Rust, R. S., 1883
    - Sanborn, J. E., 1887
    - Sanford, A. B., 1884
    - Sanford, E. B., 1869-1926
    - Scofield, W. E., 1909-1910
    - Scudder, M. L., 1874
    - Shanklin, W. A., 1908-1912
    - Sharpe, B. F., 1887
    - Shonk, G. W., 1899
    - Shute, W. G., 1914
    - Sleeper, J., undated
    - Smiley, C. W., 1882
    - Smith, A. L., 1923
    - Smith, E. M., undated
    - Smith, F. H., 1907
    - Smith, O., 1888
    - Smith, S. K., 1885, 1903
    - Smith, W. B., 1910
    - Smith, W. W., 1890
    - Starkes, H. A., 1894
    - Steele, D., 1882-1911
    - Steele, G., 1886
    - Stiles, S. M., 1897
    - Strout, E. C., 1914
    - Sutherland, A. E., 1918
    - Sutton, H. C., 1904
    - Taft, M. L., 1883
    - Taylor, S. N., 1921
    - Thorndike, E. L., 1913, undated
    - Tillett, W. F., 1908
    - Tilton, J. L., 1894, 1907
    - Tinkler, C. P., 1889
    - Trafton, G. H., 1903
    - Underhill, A. S., 1898-1903
    - Upham, F. B., 1899-1903
    - VanBenschoten, J. C., 1884-1885
    - Van Dusen, W. W., 1891
    - Van Vleck, E. B, 1911, 1925
    - Van Vleck, J. M., 1877-1912
    - Waldo, C. A., 1890
    - Warren, H. W., 1879
    - Warren, H. M., 1880
    - Warren, W. F., 1915
    - Welch, H., 1897-1925, undated
    - Westgate, G. L., 1870-1880, undated
    - Westgate, L. G., 1893-1907, undated
    - Whedon, D. A., 1874-1879, undated
    - Whedon, D. D., 1866-1877
    - Whedon, J. S., 1869, undated
    - White, H. S., 1905
    - White, L., 1895
    - Whitney, D. D., 1886
    - Whitney, H. C., 1885
    - Williams, H. C., 1886
    - Wing, J. E., 1915
    - Wood, T. B., 1891-1908
    - Woods, W. C., undated
    - Wood, J. R., 1877
    - Woodruff, W. E., 1887-1888
    - Yager, G., 1911
    - Yard, J. M., 1927
- Series 2. Teaching and Education, 1869-1928
  The Teaching and Education series includes record books, lecture notes, examination questions, and tributes and memorials. The record books document student grades for the courses taught by Rice. His lecture notes cover subjects including botony, geology, mineralogy and crystallography, zoology, and science and religion. The examination questions include those used by Rice in his own teaching, as well as entrance examination questions for Wesleyan University and other New England colleges and universities. The tributes and memorials to Rice, as well as obituaries, offer information about Rice's teaching and scholarly career. Also included in this series is a hand-drawn sketch of Rice made by Mrs. Calvin Sears Harrington.
  - Class record books, 1869-1918 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    These 7 folders contain 32 class record books.
  - Class record books, 1869-1918 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    This folder contains 4 class record books.
  - Lecture notes, 1879-1918
    - Botany, 1879-1882 and undated (Folder 2-4)
    - Classification of minerals, undated (Folder 5)
    - Crystallography, 1887-1893 and undated (Folder 6-7)
    - Crystallography and Optical Mineralogy, 1884-1885 and undated (Folder 8-9)
    - Descriptive Mineralogy, 1885-1899 and undated (Folder 10-13)
    - Geology, 1881-1899 (Folder 14-18)
    - Geology, 1899-1918 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Geology - Bibliographical references (Folder 4)
    - Historical Geology, 1894 (Folder 5)
    - Optical Mineralogy, 1887-1894 (Folder 6-7)
    - Physiology, 1881-1884 (Folder 8-9)
    - Science and Religion, 1896-1898 (Folder 10)
    - Vertebrata, undated (Folder 11)
    - Zoology, 1880-1885 and undated (Folder 12-14)
    - Miscellaneous lecture and laboratory notes (Folder 15)
  - Examination Questions
    - 1873-1888 (Folder 16)
    - Yearly entrance examinations and prize examinations for the New England colleges, 1866-1894
      These are entrance examinations for various New England Colleges: Harvard, Tufts, Amherst, Williams, Dartmouth, Boston University, University of the State of New York, Cornell, and Wesleyan; there are also various examinations for special prizes (Phi Beta Kappa, etc.).
      - Entrance and prize examinations, 1866-1894 (Folder 17-18)
      - Entrance and prize examinations, 1866-1894 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Request by students for address, 1873 (Folder 4)
  - Election to Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1871 (Folder 5)
  - Testimonials, Obituaries, and Memorial Resolutions, 1924-1928 (Folder 6-7)
  - Sketch of William North Rice by Mrs. Calvin Sears Harrington, undated (Folder 8)
- Series 3. Publications, Addresses, and Sermons, 1867-1955 (bulk 1867-1927)
  The Publications, Addresses, and Sermons series contains materials created by Rice. An index of sermons and publications can be found at the beginning of the series. Following the index, Rice's writings are divided into the following topics: Wesleyan University, Education, Geology and Science, and Religion. The religion section includes sermons as well as other writings on the topic of religion. Within each topic, writings are arranged chronologically.
  - Index of sermons and publications (Folder 9)
  - Wesleyan University
    - Personal History of the Class of 1865, Wesleyan University, July 1865-July 1867, 27 pages, William N. Rice, Editor, Brooklyn, 1867 (Folder 10)
    - Inauguration of President Cyrus D. Foss, including address by William N. Rice, Hartford Daily Times, 27 October 1875
    - Wesleyan University, Scribner's Monthly, Vol. XII, No. 5, September 1876
    - In Memoriam: Prof. John Johnston, College Argus, 8 December 1879
    - Wesleyan University, Daily Christian Advocate, 12 May 1896
    - Chapter LXVII: Wesleyan University, in The New England States, circa 1897
    - Draft of paper on co-education, later revised for pamphlet titled Papers on the Relation of Wesleyan University to the Higher Education of Women, 1899
    - Papers on the Relation of Wesleyan University to the Higher Education of Women, 1900
    - The Wesley Bicentennial, North American Review, Vol. 176, No. 6, June 1903 (Folder 11)
    - The Curriculum of Wesleyan University, Wesleyan Literary Monthly, June 1905
    - The History and Work of Wesleyan University, address by William N. Rice, from Celebration of the Seventy-Fifth Anniversary of the Founding of Wesleyan University, 1907
    - The History and Work of Wesleyan University, an Address delivered by Professor William North Rice, Ph. D., LL.D., at Middletown, Conn., Sunday June 17, 1906, in Commemoration of the Seventy-Fifth Anniversary of the Founding of the University, Part I, Christian Advocate, Vol. LXXXI, No. 27, 5 July 1906
    - The History and Work of Wesleyan University, an Address delivered by Professor William North Rice, Ph. D., LL.D., at Middletown, Conn., Sunday June 17, 1906, in Commemoration of the Seventy-Fifth Anniversary of the Founding of the University, Part II, Christian Advocate, Vol. LXXXI, No. 28, 12 July 1906
    - History and Work of Wesleyan University, Zion's Herald, 4 July 1906
    - News clippings regarding coeducation at Wesleyan, baccalaureate address, installation of President Shanklin, 1908-1910 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Sentence conferring degree of Doctor of laws on Frank B. Weeks, June 1909
    - The Van Vleck Observatory: dedication booklet, Address at the Ground-Breaking, and prayer at the dedication, June 1914
    - Address of Professor Rice, President Raymond's Memorial Service, Wesleyan Literary Monthly, vol. 24, March 1916
    - Through Darkness to Dawn, Cardinal, Spring 1955
    - The History of Wesleyan University, Lecture VIII, Course in Fundamentals of Student Life, 28 September 1917
    - Address on Woodrow Wilson, Wesleyan University Alumnus, May 1924
    - Historical Sketch of Wesleyan University, 1926
    - Our Half Century, Middletown Scientific Association adddress, 8 March 1927
  - Education
    - Shall I Go to College?, undated (Folder 2)
    - Claims of the Educational Institutions of Methodism, Proceedings of the Methodist Convention of the State of Connecticut, 1869
    - The Educational Work of Methodism, Baltimore Centennial Daily, 18 December 1884
    - Natural Science as a Branch of Education, College Argus, 1 February 1886
    - Science Teaching in the Schools, American Naturalist, September-October 1888
    - Plea for more adequate preparation in the secondary schools for the study of natural science in the colleges, New England Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools, Addresses and Proceedings at the Fourth Annual Meeting, 1889 (Folder 3)
    - Science-Teaching in the Schools, an address delivered before the American Society of Naturalists, 1889
    - Report of the Committee of the American Society of Naturalists on Science Teaching in the Schools, 1890
    - Speech on Natural Science as a Requirement for Admission to College, The New England Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools: Addresses and Proceedings of the Sixth Annual Meeting, 1891
    - The High School and its Relation to Other Educational Institutions, Special Report of the Board of Education of the Middletown City School District, 1896
    - Report of the dedicatory exercises at the opening of the new high school of the Middletown City School District, 26 March 1896
    - Education in Middletown, speech listed on the agenda of the Celebration of the Two-Hundred and Fiftieth Anniversary of the Settlement of Middletown, Connecticut, 10-11 October 1900